hey everyone and welcome to another
awakening from the meaning crisis
discord q a
this is part three of our
trilogy through nick b's
journey or his tale of intrigue
and through his life in four cults
and uh he's taken us through
uh quite a bit and now today we're going
to be focusing on
i guess the the do's and don'ts of
of how to how how to
if you're gonna have a cult how to have
a good call
[Laughter]
i'll pass it uh i'll pass it to you in
it
great yeah so we ran through a
a couple of these uh tenets at the end
of the last video
um and perhaps we can just kind of go
through them as they come up
instead of listing it
kind of like i did last time as i was
rushing
um yeah so
i maybe a good starting point would be
dealing with
arguably the two traits that come up
most obviously
when we think of the word cult kind of
its popular image
within the culture and that's generally
narcissism
and authoritarianism um
so those are like the the big you know
when you hear
the boogeyman word of cult it's
generally you're thinking of an
extraordinarily narcissistic
leader that has an extreme authoritarian
rule
over the group of people that they're
convinced of whatever
so part of you know when i make
arguments in in this realm has been you
know part of my argument against why
cult is not a particularly useful word
is because a lot of really good work has
been done
on these uh
qualities in other fields
and everything you can learn from those
applies directly to these larger group
situations or
even small just group situations
um and so i don't think it's actually
doing very much to use the word
cult as a normative boundary in that
sense
instead it's it's a lot more useful for
a person
to move the normative boundary to the
descriptor
so right oh this is a narcissistic
cultic structure can give someone more
tools
because they know what narcissism is
whereas the word cult is too
fuzzy and kicks in someone's uh
defensive reactions perhaps
um so it in that regard
a book that i found very useful um
was was daniel shaw's traumatic
narcissism
um and then it's i forget the subtitle
it's like
systems of subjugation or something like
that
um but he he gives an interesting frame
because he kind of stacks it
he starts from an individual personal
relationship
layer of dealing with narcissism and and
narcissistic parents or
close people in the in your family and
then he kind of builds it up from there
looking at at how that narcissistic
quality can develop
into these larger systems
and one of the chapters is devoted to
his time
in a cult that was based in hinduism
although he never actually says which
one it was
so yeah this is
really tricky a really tricky aspect of
this
scenario as well because narcissism has
gone
so wildly out of control like it's just
the
the normal mode of behavior now
to be extraordinarily narcissistic like
that's what
social media is it's it's it
fosters extreme narcissism it just in
this
in the sense of attention seeking and
then the
distorted sense that forms when you have
a a system where you have a a um
an audience and a uh a performer
right that scenario leads very deeply to
narcissistic
uh seeking a lot of this also comes from
from the mechanism by which we validate
our identities
so like narcissism is also a necessary
and healthy
quality of what it means to be a person
so learning kind of like how to
properly contextualize narcissism why it
exists
and then how it can go kind of sliding
into
you know the familiar nasty territory
um all of that is is very important to
get a handle on
um and again i would say
probably now more so than ever
because of its extreme prevalence but
right
it's you know being an instagram or a
youtube star
or whatever like all of this is is
uh the beginnings of just classic
narcissistic cultic structures
forming around individuals and it's
often in ways that we're not entirely
familiar with because we're also used to
with the word cults or you know a
thought leader or whatever
we're often used to the isolationist
quality that's
easy to point out in the physical world
and really hard to point out
in the digital world um hard because
generally um people will self enclose in
a
right echo chamber or kind of thought
bubble
it's usually completely open to anyone
that wants to go and look at what's
happening there
like there's very little boundaries most
of the time
um so yeah
i don't know it's missing a lot of the
qualities that normally set off our red
flags
uh right even even this group uh not
be too harsh here but right one of the
barriers of entry is having watched
50 hours of one guy's lecture series
granted you can come in and have
conversations without that but
it will be reinforced by the people that
if you want to deeply
partake in the conversations we're
having here that's kind of like a
a standard requirement
and that's going you know i don't know
it's
potential for for that type of thing to
start forming into uh personality cults
is is very easy and you see it with
anyone else
you know jordan peterson or i don't know
i'm picking certain people here but that
people would be familiar with
that you know it's it's possible with
literally
anybody nowadays
uh but i'm wondering a bit here
learn about narcissism is the main point
there and then
that learning is very useful because it
applies in every social circumstance in
which you'll encounter it
uh rather than than trying to use a lens
that's not particularly
helpful of trying to
do the normative boundary uh policing
of what is a cult and what isn't
so that was a nice 10 minute rant
i don't know if anyone has comments on
narcissism
uh i i have a comment
so i do agree with you on narcissism as
part of
the cult kind of the standard cult
understanding what my experience was
that i i i've seen
in my experience with the cult like the
mo
the destructive one i've been in i
noticed that
there are people who are like
overt narcissists but also there are
people who are
kind of convert narcissists like
or or they are so traumatized that they
are like
trauma bonding or whatever the term is
i'm not a psychologist
but right essentially like it becomes
kind of stable system
in a way and also the
some of the people who are not alert
narcissists
they are actually kind of aspiring to
become like the next leader
of some sort that's my kind of i can't
prove it but it was my feeling does it
matter yes and i think
getting like a clear handle on the whole
uh the work that's been not
done on narcissism is helpful because it
pops us out of our
our classic training you know the really
overt
signs of narcissism that most people can
recognize
and it gets a lot more refined and
one of the comments perhaps to your
point that i said
in i think in the last one was about
how naivety is a form of narciss
like most of what fuels naivety
is narcissism and
having this kind of
there yeah you're exactly right there's
a very bizarre effect where our own
sense of narcissism makes us way more
likely to be manipulated by another
narcissist
because in some sense we are realizing
our dream through the that person we are
projecting it and we'll
subjugate ourselves with the dream that
will be the mighty
narcissist at some later point
um so that yeah maybe our own narcissism
can work against us in multiple
ways in that regard one is is the
projecting on to the person what we want
to be
and then the other is just
opening us up to levels of manipulation
that you would not
necessarily uh
be as open to without a culture-wide
emphasis on uh narcissistic behavior
and following up on this i have this
observation that
the cults have this kind of i mean
narcissistic cults as you call them
they have this weird usefulness
because a person can go on
being manipulated for whatever or not
aware delusional
narcissistic whatever you want to call
it until they actually hit
a more sophisticated narcissist which is
usually a cult leader
and then they hit the wall
and this becomes kind of a realization
in a way
right but sometimes sometimes it turns
badly but sometimes it's just an
awakening moment
in a way oh and they they start to see
their own nursing field
so in this respect it's kind of weirdly
useful
right i mean that's a it's a important
point to bring up
right it's like just because a system is
is uh relatively horrifying does not
mean people are not
learning a great deal from it yeah
um and you know part of that confusion
can be used against uh well it can be
used within
a cultic structure um yeah
so you know
there's always learning to be had from
whatever
bad circumstances we happen to find
ourselves in
um okay but we should ideally if
if we're consciously going into a
situation
like in this group where people are
trying to design a religion
i think it would it's probably helpful
to have a very clear idea of how very
wrong those things can go
yeah also your good intentions don't
protect you from
anything at all right every cult i've
been in
had but legitimately honestly good
intentions
um so yeah that's part of that naivety
right
it's like yeah but that's a good point
like how
groups of people do get delusional as
well
as individuals this is i find that
fascinating
right well what i noticed as well was
like a very slow slide
um from the means
are more important to the ends to the
ends justify the means
and it was not obvious where the switch
happens
so there's just this slow
movement right especially if your means
are not performing as well as you would
hope
then there's just this like keep your
eye on the prize
thing that starts popping up and then
eventually you'll realize that you start
you know you're willing to sacrifice
more and more
uh for the accomplishment of that goal
uh until you end up in
a full you know arguably uh heavily
delusional state
yeah thank you
i have a question so
regarding confirmation bias and then the
replication crisis in psychology
um do you think it's hard to use
um psychological theories as concrete
models
as concrete models absolutely i think
they can still be very helpful for
training a person's salience but every
time i read
especially psychoanalysis which is like
a
weird-ass branch of psychology
i take it with a huge grain of salt and
i try and make use of it and
it you know allow it to inform my own
experiences on things but i try not to
just
i don't know the hard sciences are a lot
easier to let them
impact me more than the soft sciences
one should be i think deeply skeptical
just to draw off that when you talked
about branding
and um kind of internalizing
whatever that brand or identity might be
i i'm worried
about with psychology um whatever pop
theory might be uh
relevant at the time it might um make
your salience landscape
identify with whatever is popular in the
theory
and so something like um like
christianity being popular and that's
like
the supernatural model of the universe
and you internalize that
like that's not going to be you know
accurate and so
regarding that i just uh i'm not really
sure if it's
a good idea to model your salience
landscape based on something that we
don't know
um exists in any real sense
i would agree however i would say that
again
we end up cutting up cutting a balance
between
two dangers one is like you can't throw
away
all your sense making tools because
they're fuzzy
and then at the other end you can't take
them too seriously
because they are fuzzy well that's
pretty broad in general because
psychology is just one field of science
and it's not even a
fully accurate or fully replicable
um field yet and so that would be like
saying um
like oh we can't throw away
christianity's supernatural claims
because they help us make sense of the
world
i think it's um misleading
i guess yeah um i mean
looking at the work in many ways then
it's like why listen to what
anyone has to say um
well if there's evidence then that's a
good start if there's replication that's
a good start i'm just
speaking because you're talking about
narcissism which is a theoretical
model in psychology and then psychology
isn't
like it would be like if you're trying
to scientifically prove
astrology for example and then there was
no evidence and i said well maybe
this isn't the best way for us to look
at astronomy
through the lens of astrology for
example
so would you say that we should be
looking at neuroscience
uh i wouldn't i wouldn't be making any
prescriptive claim beyond
the claim i just made just because i
don't know
i don't know like how to deal with this
idea of the cult i'm not even
fully sure what it what it entails
because you've brought up the history of
how the words have changed
and so i'm trying to get the general
pattern um
i guess when you bring up narcissism as
the general theme
or a general theme uh it becomes even
cloudier just because the
theory might not even be accurate to
human nature
um i mean yeah
i agree and
yet it seems fairly obvious that there
are
healthy and unhealthy personality types
and we've classified a certain class of
them
under a term that has an arguable basis
for
where it arises from and yet it seems
fairly obvious when one is interacting
with an
extreme narcissist that something is
wrong
well i i do i do have uh objections but
i don't want to take over
the conversation so i'll allow someone
else to make a
question or conjecture i can add that
there is something called
dark triad which is more generic term
than just narcissism
and there are scales in experimental
psychology how they
measure it so it's not it's not
completely theoretical
there is some kind of statistical
evidence
right well and part of the problem is
that it's statistical evidence
so you're within a field like with
psychology you're largely
basing it off of an overton window that
you can't tell
where it is on a objective scale
so you're establishing normal and then
you're judging things against whatever
that idea of normal is
right and that's where the confirmation
bias comes but anyways i
like if anyone else finds this like
juicy yeah an important point
i just don't want to take over the
conversation i think it would be
not a good move to just go all of it is
meaningless make sense no i'm not i'm
not saying that i'm saying
it's not proven and so to use it as if
it was proven is misleading
right well and yeah that's why i was
hedging everything with
the um you know take it with a grain of
salt okay use it fair enough use it to
help
perfect inform your own experience i'm
not saying
psychology is a perfect field by any
stretch of the imagination
psychoanalysis
which is where daniel shaw's writing is
arguably way sketchier than
even the larger category of psychology
okay thanks man
but the group sense making of a lot of
other people
does help just yes be skeptical you know
keep a certain layer of
your autonomy
uh manuel did you have something i cut
you off there
at one point oh i i just wanted to say
right
when when we caught another area
right then we might not have the exact
area according off but there's still an
area right like if it's a little bit
larger or a little bit smaller doesn't
matter right like we're still describing
a thing
and i think that's important to notice
and
narcissism part right like we might not
be accurate but we
are accurate enough to talk about a real
thing
right well and i don't think we
shouldn't lose focus that you weren't
talking just about narcissism but
narcissism with totalitarianism
and authoritarianism that you know there
are a lot of narcissists out there who
don't
you know just impose their will on on a
group
and yeah right well usually they'll
i just i just isolated a narcissism just
as a psychological theory
that's all
right um and it is
it is if you do look into the work a
little bit
like there is it's not just bad
it's part of identity formation and how
one right narcissism is the appropriate
response to realizing one's
size in the universe i've heard one
person
say interesting
psychologist right it's it's how you
make it's
in some very deep sense what is
protecting you from nihilism
um so right
again it's probably a lot more uh
helpful to speak
in terms of what does a healthy
narcissistic attitude look like
and what does a unhealthy one look like
and authoritarianism might be one aspect
we
bring in to look at how narcissism can
be
very damaging
when it's taken out of a certain
circumstance
or push too far in a certain way
um all right let's see are we good on on
can we should we bring some other stuff
in here
yep yes please
um this one i brought up last time to
the bait and switch of surrender
and uh to submission
this one's exceptionally common for
getting people through
through the door and kind of altering
their normal sense
so right in any type of transformative
practice
now we're looking at a very specific
subset of
cultic structures that this
group that we're in is specifically
aimed towards
which is how do you transform people um
great the word cult also applies to
political projects and
many other things but
this one is really uh pretty uh tricky
because i i think it's damn near
impossible for a person to within
themselves
identify meaningfully the difference
between surrender and uh
and submission at a phenomenological
level um and i can say that
from my own personal experience it was
having an experience of surrender that
was not oriented towards
any person um
that opened me up for being
for for confusing it with submission
and chasing after the experience of
surrender
through submission which was again i'm
relying on a psychoanalyst's
work here um emmanuel uh
gent g-h-e-n-t
um yeah
in in some deep sense it's like upon
realizing the deep relaxation of
sleep you smash yourself in the head
with a hammer to try and replicate it
and that obviously has negative
consequences this one's really tricky
and especially because um
part of verveiki's project in particular
is
reintroducing the communal
aspect of the the kind of transformative
project which has largely been stripped
away
in a good number of of the secular
projects that have made it into the west
that are spiritual in some sense
right so spirituality in the west has
through the new age kind of taken on
this tone of like your personal
journey and then it falls into this auto
didactism
that uh verbage critiques rightly
and then the problem is that it's
putting us in back in the dangerous
position
of how do you find something that is
worth your surrender
um and probably more
more familiar
to phrase it in a more familiar sense
what's something that's worthy of your
submission
um so right i'll i'll try and pull it to
an example that is
uh hopefully less contentious than
uh transformation in a spiritual sense
why is a college worth you submitting to
right and it's it's created all the i
mean you're you're literally paying
enormous amounts of money to be properly
brainwashed
and then by being properly brainwashed
you
are affording yourself the ability to
offer more value to the people around
you
right this is the college system and
ideally
you also feed that value back into the
college system itself by making
advancements in the field
but right it's it's well-known
confirmation by us among them
that it is it requires us to be
taught a certain memetic structure in
order to even
have a chance at coming up coming to
um valuable or pseudo-objective
information right it takes a lot of work
of reframing how the human mind normally
operates
to try and cleanse it of its normal
issues
so right we we often
perhaps more relevant culturally as well
as we can see what happens when a
trusted structure like a college which
is in the business of
properly brainwashing people um allows
things or things get into its system
that are not
uh healthy so
right people pay you know whatever
they're 80 grand for their degree
and then they get programmed into
someone's pretty overt
cultic system um
and then they get a piece of paper
saying this is what makes them valuable
to the rest of the society
and you can end up very quickly and
pretty serious issues
now all of those issues have been held
at
bay largely from modernism's bend
focus and they're they're sliding out
and i would say that
almost all of those mechanisms are
non-existent
for keeping it at some level of purity
when you get into transformative
practices
particularly when you move away from
purity-oriented
religious practices because they do have
a clear measuring standard
but when you get into stuff like young's
integrating the shadow
or you know
all these you know crazy wisdom
in many ways it's just you know guru
gets to do whatever he wants and it's
your job
to figure out how whatever the hell he
happens to do
is some great part of some great
spiritual practice
right that's a very dangerous position
to be
it um so
you're trading between safety and
effectiveness constantly
here you know being an individualist is
arguably safe
you might be extremely deluded but at
least you're deluded unto yourself
and not onto a group of people um it
if you're going into a group situation
it's ability to have a transformative
effect is going to be
way higher than your auto didactical
process
but it's going to open you up for
changes that are
not guided by you and are arguably
dangerous
and then when it gets into really
effective spiritual practices
like integrating a shadow or you know
these
darker you know crazy wisdom type
things that have the potential to create
transformation much more quickly
the danger level starts shooting through
the roof
and usually people especially in our
cultural climate where we expect
instantaneous return on our investment
um it's really gonna that's that's like
a major thing to be really
aware of um
and right the other there's dangers on
the other side as well like a purity
culture
now you have something to measure
against you can tell who's full of shit
and who isn't
you also run into the normal
really deep dogmatic and fundamentalist
attitudes that come with purity cultures
and you can often end up you know
especially
in this circumstance recreating the same
thing you were trying to deal with
or avoid so
there's dangers on every side here i i
think
probably you know if we look at some of
the
examples of the systems that work the
best
best in really heavy quotation marks
here
um creating systems that have numerous
levels of checks and balances is
seems to be a clear helpful quality
sometimes that can undermine the
authority and then you end up in an
infinitely
fracturing system that's almost like
protestantism
right i don't know it's just
you're trading between variables
constantly here and perhaps what would
be helpful
is something like for vicki's ecology of
practices
but for sociological structures
and kind of framing things from how do
you keep this dynamic
balance through multiple uh
forms of practice rather than isolating
down
to you know there is uh health and
here's exactly what it looks like
type of formation
anyone have ideas for dealing with that
enormous cluster of problems see i don't
i don't have any answers here it's just
explorations and having witnessed
how many different ways stuff can go
sideways
so it's good this is probably going to
be very deeply unsatisfying
can you repeat that last part about
healthy systems
right so i was i was taking into account
um verveiki's ecology of practices
which is a way that he tries to avoid
some of the issues that come up
with um older religious structures
and basically just because you meditate
does not mean you're not
bullshitting yourself matter of fact it
greatly increases the chance that you
will bullshit yourself
um so how do you take a practice
make use of it without it creating the
extreme propensity for bullshit and so
his answer was well if i balance
meditation
against this practice and this practice
and this practice
they all kind of like dirty hands
washing each other
have a greater chance to to recognize
and deal with the bullshit that comes
out of one practice
um by you know it becomes revealed in
another practice
so i was trying to use it as a metaphor
for
perhaps how we might create then in that
sense how we are creating a healthy
spiritual practice i'm trying to extend
that to how do we create a
healthy spiritual community or
you know something like that so let's go
like john's 50 hours of video
one of his main reasons for that
is i think to answer the question how do
you choose what you submit to
you know he wants to convince you that
the things
he's advocating for are justified based
on
based on science and history and
philosophy and
rather than just saying hey do this
because i tell you to
right right the problem then is you end
up in the post-modern critique of
anyone can weave any story
well or there could be multiple stories
that lead to similar
results and i think that's that's fair i
i don't think
i don't think anyone here john
especially would say hey this is the
only way to do it
you know there's a bunch of different
practices that achieve similar
types of insight you know cultivation
and
you know he's not going to say well you
have to do my way if you do some other
way
if it's shown to be effective reliably
effective
you know he would say hey that's that's
a great way too
right so that might be considered one of
those
checks and balances right so
what are you using to measure what
success is
and then how open are you to having
multiple
pathways of success um i i do
think
again you're you're constantly trading
off between things
right so when you when you open up
yourself to that argument
you are likewise opening yourself up to
a infinitely fragmenting culture
that can't act until you kind of like
settle back down to the individual
and it's just whatever works for the
individual
works and that's all there is to it and
now you've lost the communal aspect
you've lost the
wisdom transmission outside of what a
person
autodidactically picks up and says i
find use in this
again protestantism is a useful example
here because you you can like
watch a unified religion fragment
infinitely
nick have you explored the institutional
structures inside the church
and how they keep healthy uh a little
bit
um you know i la in the last
uh talk i used uh orthodox christianity
as a good example of a system that has a
hard in easy out policy
and how that might work so
right anyone's allowed into the church
to listen to any sermon or whatever
they get it's open in that sense easy in
but it's it takes a lot of dedication
and time
and practice and interacting with the
community until you're actually
considered a
member of the church yeah it was your
granted
i was more referring to the ecology of
practices
for the institution
the ecology of practices for the
institution
yeah so i mean it's much more
clearly bound within a system like
catholicism
like most of us are familiar with at
least some of the
rituals that are performed uh and then
when you get into protestantism it's
basically whatever the hell you know
there's some limitation based on the
denomination you're claiming
but largely it's whatever the church
wants
to practice um
yeah so yeah so you don't see any direct
solutions or
copy paste of all things that is where
i'm trying to go
do i see any direct no i don't i don't
again
i'm trying to outline the problems to
give a sense
for the space to play in and then
ideally use examples of like
this seems to work better than this
thing over here
um yeah i have a comment
so when i got out of the car
i worked with a few therapists and
i kind of got to see how
the therapist community operates in the
uk at least
and they have a lot of checks and
balances and supervision and
institutions where they train and blown
program of training and
and there is a lot of
boundaries they have to follow and check
like if if they were teaching a student
and then the student wants to get
romantically involved with them they
have to wait
for like three years before doing
anything
right and even then they have to do it
they supervise them
there is a lot of this stuff otherwise
they are just
kicked out and lose their accreditation
right
and i wasn't aware of this before i
started to do any
self development let's say yeah
yeah i mean it's oh sorry continue
i was surprised i mean i mean they still
go off
at times but i feel
it's a good kind of structure because
it's not completely
centrally authoritarian
it's more like collegial
right right and i think that is very
like having really clear boundaries
is definitely a sign you know you need
especially when you're entering into
such fuzzy territory
um yeah it helps to have like as a
narcissist you need to have a clear
boundaries and you so you need to be
aware of your
own boundaries and this is the process
of learning by bumping against
narcissists
right right right yeah
yeah so that would probably you know
incorporating stuff like that
into something like a retina would
probably be extremely useful
you know certainly having a deep
awareness of of how that whole
scenario works again i i do think
there's an interesting
trade-off um
i don't know i i haven't actually seen
any research on the subject so it would
be
interesting because a a guru type figure
is in many ways
fulfilling the role of a therapist plus
a lot more and so it would be
interesting to see
people's experiences of transformation
within themselves
in therapy compared to uh various
spiritually oriented or religiously
oriented systems
um yeah what would the lot more be
oh sorry alexi go ahead oh and the
follow-up on that
so after getting out of that cult i
spoke to a therapist who was
at the same cult as me but he went there
deliberately to
to grow because it's like group work and
group work in therapy is the most
efficient
provided there are good facilitators
and i asked him how
how does it work when it's when the
group
therapy is really good and he said in
one case
they had the situation where the
facilitator was not strong enough
and essentially a few members of the
group just
kicked him out and continued so they
they got for a retreat
and and after a couple of days they
decided that the facilitator is not good
he was out and they and and they
continued and got to a good kind of
place oh interesting yeah
yeah so it's kind of distributed
cognition maybe
as john puts it right but then but then
the the people have to be kind of on a
similar level
yes yeah and you're gonna encounter the
problem
of like what do you how do you deal with
people that are like seriously damaged
and offer them something that is you
know
legitimately useful for them um
yeah a lot of it's like what's
the scope of what you're in yeah i'm
just throwing this because yeah no no
that's that's a good
yeah didn't mean to uh yeah argue
against it so much as
uh nuance it a bit
um yeah and and uh adam your question
what's the a lot more
it would be say inducing um religious
experience
bringing a person into contact with some
type of supernatural thing
offering a community offering a communal
structure
like the actual how the community itself
operates
there's a lot that a guru can do that a
therapist is more limited ability
largely because of the institutional
structure
very often
gotcha thank you
do we have questions queuing up in in
event text
there's there's a couple general there's
a couple general questions
uh but i don't know if you wanted to do
those at the end
as general ones or right or throughout
yeah if they're general then we can kind
of keep pushing through let's see we're
at an
hour already so maybe
oh i wanted to keep this one a little
bit shorter hopefully
but we'll see
um all right let me let me try and make
it a little bit
further through the list and
see where we end up
so yes when you're dealing with
transformative uh
communities as a very general rule
you need some mechanism for enabling
surrender
and then to have a mechanism to
account for the slide into submission
uh last time i used the example of
dialogos
as they is a practice built
to allow surrender with ideally without
allowing it to slide into submission but
the propensity is there
as some people commented watching some
of uh
guys saying stocks videos of of circling
um so
right it's it's it's ever present i but
you're gonna
have to figure out that calculus of of
uh
of putting someone in a state where they
can wear
transformation is afforded and not used
against them
and that's that's hard to hard to pull
off but we we played around a little bit
there with some
some like um
and yes the side effect of that is the
more you move away from a system like
dialogos
and closer into a system of like classic
student-teacher dynamics um
arguably the more effective the actual
transmission will be
and the far more dangerous it will be
and it will have a much stronger
propensity to become
a uh a submission based
system rather than a surrender based
system
how i'm using those words would probably
be helpful
to read emmanuel gents paper on it
it's only like 15 pages a lot of woo
and funky stuff in there but i think he
is pointing towards
something useful to pull apart
so um
so yeah a question that i saw come up
in one of the other uh channels in here
was people dealing with the issue of how
do you pick a teacher
and it's it's this kind of endless
chicken or egg problem of like only the
wise recognize the wise
right like you can't actually pick a
teacher
unless you're already at the level of
teaching otherwise you are
kind of blindly relying on some other
structures
process in order to trust the
information
coming in or you will be endlessly stuck
in a uh combinatorial explosion if you
will
use a verveikian term here um
yeah go for it iron root oh no i was
just making the explosion
oh um
so one of this is tying back into the
narcissism
from earlier as well but you know i
think a mechanism that people are
or something people are looking for and
have a
really hard time getting a grasp of is
this
this difference between narcissistic
power
and ontological power and they often
look alike and have a really different
uh phenomenology underlying them
so right to use classic his you know
religious examples we can use the buddha
or
christ both of them could be described
as extraordinarily narcissistic people
um right one saying he is the son of god
the other saying he is truly enlightened
you know like extraordinarily
narcissistic claims
but the larger question is not the
immediate appearance but what is the
actual
on the the ontological
sense emanating from them and compare it
to someone like say donald trump
who is more familiarly um
putting out this sense of narcissistic
power and yet you can see
it kind of in between the lines
that there's this underlying sense of a
deep
uh ontological insecurity
that's creating the the
the hot air if you will of his
is uh mirage image of of being secure in
himself
so by ontological there you mean what
their actual being is
is that what you mean by that being yes
right
right do they have a sense of security
in being itself
or do they have a sense of security in
an egoic
uh display and how do you tell the two
apart
because largely it's you can really
fudge a person's
circuits where they think they are
perceiving ontological security
and all they are is dealing with uh
the image of it
so that's an area of investigation i
think that would be interesting i don't
again i don't have any answers here but
it does seem like
a useful thing to tease apart and try
and and
explore uh ideally with a more robust
lens than what we currently have
available to us
so it'd be interesting to see if cogsi
could deal with
something like the difference that's
happening there
and what the process is as one example
um
so yeah getting into specific system
design i touched on this last time as
well
graduation versus non-graduation
this is really a big problem in
spiritually oriented groups which is
there's no graduation process
which has the side effect of you being a
perma student
this is also a critique i would squarely
level
at verveiki's project itself because it
has a
a quality of infinite searching um
so this is a good way to bind people
into a subservient position um
one of the great qualities of a system
like college is that you finish
and you prove that you've learned what
it has to offer
and then you go on and you know there's
still
rules and all that kind of stuff but you
actually go on to
you know finish your subservient role
and become
part of the leadership of whatever field
that you studied ideally
so i would say this is a quality
of what makes a healthy cultic system is
that you leave it
at some point and you go out and
interface with the world and deal with
the world on your own terms
ideally recreating a kind of a hegelian
synthesis
and improving upon what it is that you
gained by being
part of that system likewise you don't
have to actually divorce yourself from
the system
right colleges have alumni programs you
can come and teach or have guest
roles at the college these are all very
useful
things
but yeah that's that one's a big one
because
it's you know what does it mean to
graduate from a religion
it's uh confusing right does it mean
that you are truly enlightened or does
it mean that
you know the teacher has
can't offer you anything more than your
own personal investigation
like where are the limits here
you know there's a reason these systems
never stay in balance for very long
it's just difficult
issues to deal with
yeah i mean like a lot of john's jumping
in at any point here
a lot of what john's talking about
almost is way of life like the ecology
of practices
is a way of life right you know
you know it's not something you ever
gradu you ever graduate from because
you're we're all you know it's it's
tuning your brain
right to optimizing your brain for
relevance realization
right right and that's fine in this auto
didactic fashion because it's safe
enough
uh it gets a little trickier when you
start
when he for instance would go to through
the process of making an actual
community
with teachers um teaching these
ecology the ecology of practices and
then
asking the question at what point do the
students of that system
stop being students
i mean i guess i see it as that's
similar to other wisdom traditions where
i mean you've got the people who you've
got the students you have teachers and
people stop being students but they
still do their practice they're still
part of the community right
right right so that's
figuring out where that line is is
important many cultic structures you
look at do not have a process where you
are now equal with the person who taught
you
you know you're just stuck underneath
the person that taught you
forevermore and that's where you can get
into
dangerous territory
so yeah coming up with some mechanism
for how that that works
i think is an important area of
consideration you know
how much of it is actually just learning
the procedural knowledge of what the
practice is
and then how much of it is your personal
practice how does that interface with
community and how does that
interface with the community's hierarchy
all i'm doing is creating problems to
solve
here i have like zero answers in this
room
no can i just add to your last
point so when you say graduation
is very good thing
on the point that so there is this
learning element
or teaching where you kind of get to
some level but then
there is also the practice element so
it may be possible that after a point
you just keep practicing and cultivating
wisdom or whatever you want to call it
without any need to graduate or any need
to be in the same kind of
student-teacher relationship you just
become
right that's that's the point you have
to spread the meme like you need to be a
new teacher
in the next generation and also
yeah some of the students become
teachers right
i feel the frame is a little bit
restrictive if you put it this way
that has to be a graduation of some kind
of final
well i i think he's saying that
people shouldn't always be in i guess
this subservient
position to the teacher where at some
point they sort of know approximately as
much as the teacher
and you know even the teacher may be a
bit more technical
and be able to communicate it better
that the students pretty well
have grasped what the teachers offer and
you know so one point they can say i'm
not a student anymore
i'm not i'm not just always in this
under position under you
right and i mean you could apply that
same logic to college itself like when a
person graduates
do they know everything in that field no
not by
any stretch of the imagination they may
they know maybe
a single percent of the total body of
knowledge that is
that field but there is some level of
having achieved a high enough level of
proficiency to
leave the subservient position and be
able to offer something novel
onto the field um
so how do we mark that transition point
and how does it structure itself when
you start dealing with something like
the religion that's not a religion
project
i mean if that was not a project if it
was just here's some practices that work
do whatever you want with them um
this would be a lot less of a
consideration i think
for for viveki's thing in particular at
least
also dana your mouth is moving but we
can't hear you
i don't know if you're talking to us or
someone else
oh my sensitivity was too too low
i was saying that uh the religion that's
not a religion
at least to me is a framework
for an internal structure that you
develop within your own
self to kind of you know create these
structures that
do get corrupted
these external structures that that we
normally had you know such as a
church or you know whatever
hierarchy that we would subscribe to you
know the ecology of practice where
you're
your own teacher and your own student
you know you're you're it's a little
schizophrenic you're you're both
really um so that's how i take the
written our thing
at least but i i understand your concern
at least if
a traditional sort of um
system or hierarchy were to evolve out
of this
you know movement well i would say more
than that
verveiki himself claims that's the
intention
of written art it's not meant to be an
autodidactic
here's your journey for yourself he's
trying to bring back
has he said that explicitly explicitly
yeah
yeah he he he finds there's a danger to
autodidacticism
uh that you know like you know
like hitler was an autodidactic you know
look what he did i remember
i remember john uh said it
could breathe narcissism
yeah definitely it could without you
know
the proper checks on it
my critique of his critique of
autodidactism was perhaps
something that you would be in line with
as well uh which is
it seems a lot more useful to me to
train people how to make use of their
auto didactic
inclinations rather than to demonize
others well but remember like like
he doesn't consider saying what we're
doing here in this in the
discord as auto diagnostic yeah like so
so
he just says you shouldn't be doing it
on your own
like you should have a community around
you because you can bounce ideas off
they can check you when you're going off
so so here's you know so what if the
graduation process is you've
you've developed enough ability that you
can go off and start a community
of your own you know that's that's what
that is because you got to realize that
this
is only sustainable up to a certain
scale um
you know at least in this intimate of a
setting
i mean shit we can only get 25 people on
video chat anyway
you know and so
it has to be scaled out somehow
yep right and that has to be ritualized
right
or ritualized because it should be
celebrated as well
that square hat on and flip your little
thing to the other side
[Laughter]
is that the uh um the amish
no that's college oh yeah that's college
yeah i wouldn't know number one
i i just wanna i wanna draw your
attention to the time and education
so just drawing your attention to the
time
right yeah so okay yeah
uh
isolationist versus consumptive this is
another
quality that i've pointed out as a
quality of healthy versus unhealthy
cults
if your cult requires isolationism to
function
it's really bad that's the eating your
own shit right
mistaking the product for the for the
uh oh i forgot the goofy line to
tell people that they're full of shit in
a fancy way
um so basically you need a you need a
structure that's constantly interfacing
with the world as it happens
and i would argue this is also what
makes a healthy world view
in a more generalized sense so you need
a
cultic structure that consumes the world
processes it
makes sense of it and then is able to
uh trans transmute that consumptive
process into action
it's literally just modeling it off of
our digestive system
you know you go and consume something
that's not you
um and and you know combine it with the
body produce energy as a side effect and
turn that into further action
um
specializing your language we've all
kind of watched
struggle with where the line is on this
one
right you're you're forming boundaries
by using
specialized language you're also able to
create really useful heuristics that
condense a
huge body of information
you create an internal sense of
community by using specialized language
right good friends do the goofy
handshake or whatever
these are all important factors they can
also be used
against right they can create an
isolationist wall
they can make it so that you can't
communicate your ideas well
with people unfamiliar with your system
so perhaps
doing both in this case would be a good
way to do it so
allow yourself to create that
specialized language and also be
constantly trying to figure out
how you can communicate those ideas in
plain language also
um so right this is something for
example jordan peterson
was very helpful for for religious
people was that he broadened the
vocabulary
and was able to communicate religious or
spiritual ideas in a language that was
suited for people that were not
open to those forms of language
so playing with those those realms i
think is important
um
yeah apocalyptic myths in their
prevalence uh how they can be used to
shift our overton window
and also why we can't do without them
so this is just a really interesting
quality but like
across the board regardless of whether a
group is spiritual or not
there is this ins insistence
on apocalyptic myths so whether it's
you know dealing with uh politics and
bringing in the nuclear age
as part of it if you're into uh
ecosystem act you know activism
then you're bringing in global warming
um
you know obviously all the religions
have their their
really intense apocalyptic myths i think
a large part
of what creates this prevalence is that
apocalyptic myths are how we project our
own death
onto the world and then attempt to deal
with it
and in that sense they are extremely
healthy they are how
because literally
all of us will experience the apocalypse
it's just
whether it's also the apocalypse for
everyone else at the same time or
just for you um
right it's a matter of degree not of of
uh
quality um so realizing that that's
there
that it's also a necessary feature
coming to terms with death
uh and the the process by which we do so
and then also being aware of how that
can be misused against us to shift our
overton window
and make us think that certain behaviors
are now allowable
because of a a certain context
you know again trading off between
advantages and disadvantages here
um yeah you know i i don't think you'll
you'll be able to get away with any type
of
of world view that does not have some
type
of apocalyptic structure to it so then
the question becomes how do you make use
of it
effectively
yeah sorry i'm trying to run through
we again have gone for far longer than i
intended
so part four part five part five
yeah no i can't do any more
more
um so yeah purity cults and inverse
purity cults
i kind of went over this earlier talking
about how like
some of the advantages and disadvantages
the integrating the shadow
uh arguably what the left was doing
through like the
80s and 90s right he had like
the left is probably not a good term
here but the counter culture the
artistic counterculture of the time
doing things like piss christ and
you know arguably the dawning of
post-modern art
was like an inverse of a purity cult so
it was
literally trying to dirty the world
destroy the purity symbols or
make them put them in a context where
they're
you know symbols of an absolute lack of
purity
um yeah
i mean this ties into gnosticism as well
gnostic the gnostic
drive i would argue is characterized
more than
anything by the desire for
a pure state um
so whatever realm that happens in does
not have to be spiritual
right it could be a type of moral purity
like we're seeing on
on the far left right now lacking any
any metaphysics or supernatural element
um yeah i mean yeah again
the eco activists you know that's very
much a type of purity poll
or can be characterized as such
quite quite literally with pollution as
the
big bad guy there um
again yeah you're going to end up
trading off between things
you know the the problems of purity
cults are well known they lead to
repression
you end up with things like the catholic
priests scandal
um among other issues extreme dogma and
fundamentalism come with purity cults
inverse purity cults also
extraordinarily dangerous
right practicing sexual tantra with your
guru
has famously created many issues your
ability to decipher what is good from
what is bad or what is healthy
from what is unhealthy goes out the
window in
inverse purity cults you can
endless examples of that you know the
you know sex with the guru being instant
transmission
but then it ends up the guru just wants
to fuck a bunch of young women
uh right the the hindu cults where they
meditate so deeply on death that they're
eating rotting carcasses
of humans to prove that everything is
the same
or to induce it as an experience
um yeah it's just
which error which class of error do you
want to make and
how do you aim for the center if there
is one
and how do you keep it balanced all
important questions to ask oneself
uh creating a strong idea of the
difference between dependency
independency and codependency
um there's so much to say there that i'm
just gonna leave it at that
um a critique of relevance realization i
threw in here
which is this it was i brought up it i
brought it up earlier
in the chicken or egg problem of like
you can't actually tell who's a good
teacher
until you could be the teacher
um yeah so like
you know developing discernment without
any
yeah yeah i i don't know how to parse
this
so i i have like three more problems you
guys could meditate on or we could get
to some questions
and conversation
problems please problems
okay
nick do you think that uh
john's reflections on the origins of the
sacred
shed some light on or dovetails with
your
meditations on you know cultish because
it seems like he
made a link and it said it's fuzzy to me
to put to
this sacred originating in
something like a a childhood
or childlike imprint i'm using that word
imprint and i'm thinking of like the way
a duckling is
imprints on when it's patches
and that leaves such a mark that one's
proximity to that
um re-encounter with that um
sort of places the individual in touch
with their
their most their most uh
original sense of the sacred or in a way
that's
that's experienced as indisputable
right it's a little tricky because
verveiki now i'm just getting into
opinions here so we're
shifting categories slightly um
verveiki does the the move where he
tries to throw sacredness out or
uh tries to throw the sacred out
altogether
and replace it with sacredness and in
many ways i've
tried to map that in my own sense making
onto the
ground of being pursuit versus being
so in that sense i can understand why he
would describe
sacredness in the terms of
a type of childhood a
uh in the sense that i think sacredness
is is
more directly tied to the oceanic
experience
and then the sacred i would argue from
my own
experiences um is what happens
following the experience of sacredness
and that's like from the oceanic
experience can you
you can finally see what
differentiation is and how beautiful it
is
within the proper context um
so yeah as far as like tying that back
to coltic structures
this is this is a weird one because
i almost get the sense that cultic
structures are how these things
limp right they they make the pursuit
available but they don't offer anything
unto the pursuit
in some very deep sense and that would
be almost
following on like kierkegaard and tilik
uh kind of the existentialist
the existentialists and beyond
if you will um which is that at some
point you have to get
you know to the god beyond the god of
theism
otherwise you're stuck always looking at
the idol of god and not the icon
and i think that cultic structures
fundamentally opera
offer us the idols and in the very best
of them
they offer us they afford us the ability
to see the icon within the idol
but it is not by any means programmable
within
within occultic structure um
and you see this in all religious
traditions right it's like
you see it in buddhism as well like the
last thing you have to throw away
is enlightenment itself like you you
have to
you cannot become enlightened by trying
to become enlightened
um right in some deep sense you'd see it
in christianity
in the failure of work
right at some point you need grace you
have to release
uh in order to to be afforded grace
um the the issues with that have been
made very obvious by various protestant
uh
theologians uh calvin of course taking
it to its furthest conclusion
um yeah so
i i don't know did i talk on what you
were aiming at there or
yeah i mean my aim wasn't very
very narrow or tight is this i'm struck
by
the first day of school so your freshman
in high school or your first day on
college campus and there's a
a mode of being that's extremely porous
and highly imprintable
and so it seems like in that state those
encounters
have such a deep resonance that they can
reverberate down through the years
i hear people tell war stories
50 years later and they have
the whole life to talk about but what
they
reminisce on is that day they were in a
foxhole
in that cold winter storm and
it was it without lifting a finger
they suffered or underwent a revelation
that marked them or imprinted them
or characterized them so there's
something about the cult
or the sacred where each each of us is
getting nailed in a way
and there's something about us that
wants to be nailed right
and i might i might differentiate there
i mean
it really depends on kind of the lens
we're using
but it's like you know the military is
the cult
that afforded the experience in the
foxhole
right and part of that was like the
extreme training
the growing of a brotherhood between a a
squadron or whatever
um right it kind of it has all these
systems that
enable uh that scenario to reach its
peak
experience of of meaning or or reality
but the cultic structure itself did not
offer the experience
it was instead what allowed the
uh contextualized the experience
so you get kind of both affecting each
other
in a in a very deep sense right viveki's
uh
inter penetration um
which very suggestive language
i thought the same thing when he said uh
wants to be nailed
i'm used to it from
yeah this is a great conversation thanks
for doing this again by the way nick
yeah yeah absolutely
i don't know if you want your your your
name on the
internet or not now i can't reference
you
i feel awkward okay
should we answer some of these that have
built up in
sure and uh
so ilu who's not here right now to
comment uh i also spent time two years
in a cult from 18 to 20.
the governing structure was alleged to
be one of the consensus-based
decision-making
one of consensus-based decision-making
but ultimately the lack of information
flow throughout the community
enabled those in control of information
to leverage their expertise to control
things
example we defer to the finance guy and
finances etc
there was a lot of social control and
eroding of individuality
and general exploitation it was
ultimately shut down by the state as
historic abuse was uncovered
wow it was more of a comment yeah wow i
wish i could
talk to him to get more of what that
experience is like
but just on the surface this is that
type of thing
where it's like you know you think
you've come up with a rock solid
structure system that's gonna you know
work well and it's the levels
this is like what i try and talk about
with the naivety
of of people it's like thinking that
you're gonna be able to design
the one system uh that does not corrupt
horrifyingly in all of human history
it's like if if there was an answer to
this question
we would all be living in the utopia and
we would have gotten here a hundred
thousand years ago
so it's i think you underestimate mark
[Laughter]
maybe so um so yeah
again i i don't know like a way around
that than checks and balances
thinking that you know you've dodged the
problem because
you've created a system a healthy system
of
meritocracy or whatever that's not going
to corrupt
or i don't know man i don't know
it's a really intense set of problems
probably the safest to some degree is
there's a reason where an individualist
culture and it's like
individualism is so safely ineffective
that it allows people to like
live off the meager scraps of meaning
without a lot of the dangers that come
with partaking in these
uh larger social structures and we we
have not come up with a good answer for
that
so it's it as not to say we should not
be trying
it means we should be extraordinarily
skeptical in our ability to actually do
so
i'm also very aware you know try to be
very mindful of
are we succeeding and what we're trying
to accomplish and
you know what is the actual practical
effect of what we're doing
all right adam had a question but i'm
not going to talk
yeah without them well maybe we'll we'll
see if
uh talk to elu and maybe ely will want
to come and
share a bit of their experience in
another day
yeah get a call there's like three or
four of us that have
maybe more that have pretty intense cult
experience so we could get like a
for obvious reasons i mean learning from
your guy's experience is very important
to me and i know a lot of people here
yeah we want to avoid
that you know we you know we're
you know there is the danger here and we
so we're aware of it and we want to
so learn from others other mistakes adam
had a question but i think it's a bit of
an
okay so i'm sorry did you want to yeah i
was just going to no wait no it's very
serious
um oh i was just gonna throw in as well
to your
your point there brett just that uh you
know it it's even
i mean yes it's highly salient in a
group like
this one where it is it has an emphasis
on
transformative community and and also is
trying to create a
religion that's not a religion um but i
i would also argue like it's just
increasingly prevalent across the board
as people starving for meaning
um you know
it seems clear to me that postmodernism
ends in something like a whole hell of a
lot of cults
um and i don't see a clear way out of
that
yeah and that seems to be happening so
at various levels that seems to be
happening
so yeah it's all very important stuff
people that have experienced the kind of
extremes of these realms learning from
from what they have
uh experienced i think is really
important so jana's not here but she had
outside of this
but she had a question can you tell us
more about the people that were part of
the cult
what kind of reasons did they have for
ending up there and can you say
something about the difference between
people who stayed there
and the ones that were able to leave
right we skipped adam
coolest cult of all time
i don't know there's been a i don't know
i'll probably just
blanket answer with my religion to dodge
the question
so christianity is the coolest cult of
all time
uh okay so jana's question
yeah so type of people that were in the
cult there's often the character
that people that join colts are like
you know really screwed up to begin with
or or have some type of
heavy thing that makes them
open or overly suggestible
um in my experience that's not
particularly true
and like a lot of the
sometimes that's the case like the
person was at a really heavy
transitional phase in their life
um and then you just get these like
miraculous aligning of circumstances
where uh the person you know
gets funneled in at just the right
moment that's probably why
why the the j dubs are so successful at
being bringing
people in it's just like if you knock on
someone's door constantly eventually
you're gonna find the guy that was
having a midlife crisis that day
you know and takes it as a sign from god
that you knocked on their door
whatever um
so yeah there is there was some level of
like
going through a heavy transition point
in general though there was not a clear
um commonality on on the people
that i saw in those those circumstances
for people that started the cults there
was a lot more of a clear
sign and that's that they went through
some
extreme transition that resulted
in them believing they'd come to an
answer as opposed to leaving them in the
kind of
mired ground of chaos that most people
end up
in when going through transformative
experiences
um and then they tried to share that
message
usually not with the intention of
creating a cult
and then a cult forms around it as they
try and
teach whatever it is they learned
through that experience
sometimes it's more overt like the
person was like you know
normal the normal way of living sucks
i'm gonna go
build this bad ass farm and just invite
people i like to it
and then it gets weird as they try and
navigate problems in a novel way and
realize
you know they end up doing the whole
thing
it's such a broad phenomena i don't know
how to
quite answer this question as far as
the difference between people who stayed
and those that were able to leave
a lot of that came down to sunk
investment
and then that combined with just the
novel circumstances of the person's life
at that exact moment in time um
you know for me what enabled me to
break off from the one that i was like
really in because the others were fairly
easy to leave
um was was the yellow and red flag
system that i told you guys about in the
last one
um and i had like let a number of yellow
flags
slide until i got to a point where i
could see
myself recreating a situation that i had
experienced earlier that was very
traumatizing for me
um and so that was like
what kicked me out and even then i did
so with like
zero security in my decision like i did
not know if
you know the red flags that i thought
were red flags were actually red flags
or if i was just
building it up in my head right
i just couldn't tell and uh
given enough time i was proven correct
but
um well that's probably a useful project
that's why i put so much
go ahead i would say that's probably a
useful project for us is to put together
a list of these yellow and red flags
uh for us to keep in mind you know you
know
especially you know from my part instead
of organizing all this and
and and and for people to to to watch
out
to say hey maybe we're going too much in
this direction in this negative
direction
so that might be right that's something
we should work on
and it is like it's hard to
overemphasize
how important that type of system is
again when you're
especially when you're entering into an
exploratory
state dealing with a novel world view or
cultic structure
um like
you will lose your normal mechanisms
for telling one thing from another
like you you necessarily will lose those
especially if it's doing
any type of effective work on you at all
if it's totally ineffective then yeah
you're probably fine and you're also
getting nothing from
it um so yeah
that one is i i really think it is
really important and it also i think is
a good practice
for getting a person to like
learn how to
trust themselves while affording them
a a legitimately and truly and deeply
exploratory state so balancing those two
things
as as usual yeah
so i don't have anything else there i
wish i wish she was still here
because i'd like to hear a little more
about this question
but uh lemurian like crystal asks a
common superficial assessment of this
discord server by people i've invited
here is that it is culti
what can we do to change this now i'd
like to hear a little bit more about
what the specific comments were
obviously
but uh you know i think we tried
not to be uh but uh but
specialized language and the upfront
cost of 50 hours of lectures from a
single person
i would say would set off most people's
sense
um more so than anything else
i would imagine if i was coming into
this in a novel
situation that's probably what would
trigger my
my perception so so i mean this is a bit
of a rock and a hard place because
i think the educational aspects of of
that course i think are
are pretty pretty darn important for
like
like if we want people to not just
trust us to say you know that hey this
is what we're doing because it's good to
say hey
this is why we're doing it uh so without
going through the course
you don't have any idea of that unless
you have your own background
in all the stuff but the vast majority
of people probably
don't um
but but i but yeah it can seem daunting
i wonder if we should
create a just a shorter version of it
uh for people but it yeah i mean a tough
problem the intro
is a legitimate intro like people can
watch the first video in the series and
at least get an idea
and i when i pointed those out i didn't
mean to argue that we should do
something to change them
at some level there is like a
self-selection pressure that's probably
actually useful um
so can we see the cat
yeah i think brett the fundamental
problem to nick's point is
for all intents and purposes we are a
cult
right we have all of the credentials
because cults are these things that are
everywhere and so
the question is how do you get people
interested and involved without thinking
that they're going to get trapped
because the
the meditation traditions do the same
thing right they oh we're gonna
we're gonna get you enlightenment just
get some vocabulary and come on we don't
give you the book you have you read the
book
it's fine and the next thing you know i
mean that's dianetics
that's how people get into diabetics
right they read the book
well i i got all custom language there's
also the next definition of cults a
little broader i think the
the the question or this is culture the
way i was just referring to it as a more
the negative
the negative sense of you know like nick
has the
positive cult and the negative cult um
you know the idea is at least to avoid
the negative being the negative one
although i
i i i'm not convinced that cult is a
word that's
worth saving at this point that
that that it's been tarnished pretty
pretty well and
uh you know it has a negative
connotation that i think we're kind of
stuck with for a while and
i think trying to resonate trying to
save the term would be distrustful to
people
you know i think they would think oh why
are they trying to say the word cult
they're probably because they're a cult
yeah well the the other option is is you
go the normal proselytizing route and
then you're just
consumed with making sure your thing
isn't a cult when it obviously
is um yeah but i i take the criticism
it's obvious you know it's brought up a
lot that's why i try and use cultic
structure
to like strip it from some of its
connotation
while trying to get people to be more
aware
um but i think there is at some level
there's
there's a point where the gut punch i
think is useful
um or the frame break you know i i think
everyone talking about how
everything is tribal nowadays is not
it's just dodging what is actually
happening
and it's doing so in a way that does not
give us very useful
tools for dealing with the scenario well
yeah i have thoughts on that but that's
another conversation not recovering the
word is
but but i mean so so i think i mean yeah
obviously i
whether we call it i would
certainly not want people to associate
this with the negative type of cult if
they're going to associate it with
colton now
and uh i mean one one idea we played
with is you know
creating the aspirant role so there's
the the easy barrier of entry of just
anybody can come in and take part and
sit with us and all that but then for
those who want to go deeper
you know you know and make more of a
commitment you know maybe
they're they're the people who will
commit to
watching the whole series for example
and you know to following the ecology of
practices and things like that those are
you know ideas floating around right now
right and that's gonna greatly increase
the perception of
it being culty yeah
yeah i mean on the other hand you do
want people to
you do want people to have a more
invested role i think
uh and so so it's yeah it's a rock and a
hard place
it's it's yes yes at some point that's
what i'm trying to
say as well is like at some point you
just kind of go you accept
what it is you're actually attempting
you become very aware of the dangers and
risks and then you start playing with
the dynamics because if you want it to
work or have
any chance of doing anything you're
going to have to
play with those dynamics eventually
right
so then we have conversations like this
and try and deal with
the dangers but yeah as far as playing
like a pr game of
things that look culty and you know it's
like
i don't know how effective that is i i'm
far more concerned with is there any
actual
abuse or native impact on the people
that are
participating than i am with what's its
pers
public relations you know
face right
and yeah and i think with what part of
the answer is i mean like i'd like
you know if there are people who think
oh this is really culty or whatnot in
the negative sense you know what
i'd certainly like to talk to them or i
i my suggestion would be hey
hang out and tell us what you think
after that and if you have issues i mean
if people have these negative ideas
i i'd like to know about them because
maybe it's something we have to counter
you know it may be there may be
legitimate
things i mean i think we've done a
pretty good job of being very open
and yeah and
you know i think i know john is
definitely like he's
very humble he doesn't want to be like
the whole leader figurehead he wants
other people involved
part of our mandate is to you know go
with other groups you know coordinate
with other groups and that's what we've
been trying to do as well
you know be in conjunction with science
which i think is
very which is by definition
dynamic you know because science is
always changing
so practices will always change if we
want to
be in accordance with the best science
right i mean at this point i don't think
this discord has
a strong enough like yeah
if people are responding that way then
they're probably not going to get much
out of the situation anyways well that's
what i'm wondering if it's just people
who just came in looked around and then
left versus people who hung out for a
while i'd be more considerate of people
who hung out for
for a few days and then left because
they thought it was culty versus
someone who just came in and sniffed
around right in the initial
so that yeah we should probably have a
chat with lemurian like crystal
yeah i can't tell if that name is is
ironic or not
but yeah to see uh to get more
information on on that specific topic
can i add something
so um when i got out
of that cult in the uk i was written
i i found the checklist
published by a uk charity who deals with
like families of people who
disappeared in the cult and it's like
21 points which
are like celtic like negative celtic
structures usually have
and this includes things like sleep
deprivation and
[Music]
diet restrictions and
like uh not like disorienting people by
by not telling them what time it is
this kind of stuff or like not been able
to just leave physical premium
premises so i can look that up but it
sounds
similar to nick's yellow
red flag kind of system right
so so i'm saying and
following up on this you mentioned this
kind of
dichotomous like is it
open isolated or is it open
so i wonder what how would you assess
what we do here
on those measures because i feel
this community is open and
john is obviously a public figure and
everyone can
see what he's doing so there is nothing
secret or
kind of unsavory going on behind closed
doors
no yeah i would say this is very
open and then there's pseudo boundaries
formed from
investment cost right
investment in this case being a lot of
time and
brain power to understand that you know
for reiki's lecture and
where he's coming from that
contextualizes the server
um that that's not a real boundary
the only other point would be that
consumptive
aspect of like how much does the
community
use the tools available to it to
contextualize the world
um right is it isolating away from the
world and trying to escape
reality or is it dealing with it
directly
and in that regard i would also say it
has a pretty high
status of interfacing with the world as
it's happening
largely through the conversations
verveiki has with
guests and then also the conversations
we have here
well it's also baked into the the
ecology of practices themselves which
are
designed not to give you the answer
but to help you be better able to figure
out
your answers to figure out what's most
relevant
in your life and rather than saying
this is the thing that's relevant for
everybody you should all do this
it's it's
teaching you how to have maybe have more
chances of being
of having insight or or being able to
make
you know break frame you know better to
problem solve better
so rather it's not giving you the answer
it's giving you sort of
a way to help get you better answers on
your own
yeah i mean part of that i would say is
a good move and part of it i think is
is
that might be a byproduct of having an
extraordinarily small
community
when it gets to the point of like
there's a difference between this
discord
and a legitimate retina and when you get
into the question of like what's a
legitimate
uh you know religious religion that's
not a religion
um i i think a lot of what we're talking
about here will be a lot more prevalent
or more relevant
things to contend with
yeah you know so we're coming up to the
end but jay david's had a couple
questions on on
sort of the religion it's not a religion
maybe should it be have curriculum and
exams and
prerequisites and admission criteria
and you know i think john's ideas
eventually at least for some of his
things to have i mean he's doing courses
i mean you know awakening from the
meeting crisis kind of of course
he's doing the meditation course there
aren't exams but
i mean eventually i guess they're you
know you could have
actually you know classes and teachers
you know teaching
the ecology of practices and people
having to show a certain number
hours or skills to to pass
yeah yeah this is probably more
this is like getting more hands-on in
terms of like
community development
yeah that's yeah it is interesting
you were bringing up the aspirant's idea
that might be like you know you've
watched whatever x amount of time of his
content
and have a clear idea of the ideas being
discussed
and practitioner where people are
regularly
you know participating in the ecology of
practices
etc etc
but yeah unpopular indeed they send
set off people's trigger warnings
outside of
deeply accredited systems
yeah this jamie wheel video or i read
i didn't watch the video i've read his
article there's some good stuff in there
some of it i would push back slightly
against but not heavily
and then i would also make sure to say i
don't trust jamie wheel himself as far
as i can throw it
so
i haven't seen it so i will comment on
that
so well this is i probably don't want to
say that
i i don't know i have very subtle
uh little triggers in my head when i
watch
this is not the official position of
this discord
yeah i don't mean to be our guest our
guest's opinions are solely the opinion
of the guests and do not represent
from the meaning crisis discord
and the knuckleheads that post there are
also not officially
just a knucklehead from portugal shit
right so so so your goal was to do this
a little shorter and
we finished five minutes before two
hours
no no we achieved the goal the last one
went even over two hours so i think
so we did it well this has been amazing
and you know
it's actually i mean the fact that
that you could take the time and spread
it out over three
you know over six hours is is amazing i
mean i think we got so much more out of
it
because of that so yeah our deepest
thanks there nick
that's been great and and and i think
it's just the beginning honestly of this
conversation
i think you know as lemurian question
you know highlights you know this is
something that we need to be very
vigilant on
and whether you call it a cult or not we
don't want to be a bad cult
and right yeah
yes i try to make it clear like i'm not
advocating that everything calls itself
occult
i i'm trying to advocate for like a
sociological
lens that pushes a little bit closer
towards
our phenomenology so it's it's i'm
trying to incorporate
honesty as an ideal when dealing with
sociology
and then playing with it from there i'm
not saying like
this is what it is so everyone should
call itself that
but being aware that you are dealing
with cultic structures
i think is important well thank you
again
this has been great thank you for all
the questions
and uh yeah there's a lot to take in
so very much appreciated
thanks nick thanks
it was great thank you
absolutely you should hit up some of the
other folks that have been
talking about some of their cult
experiences yeah definitely a little
points and sense making that that i
don't have so yeah we might want to set
up an actual panel on that like they
have at some of the science fiction
conventions right
some of the other conventions they have
panels and we could set up a panel and
run a panel
so that might be interesting cult
convention panel
well we could set up panels on all kinds
of topics right yeah that would be the
first one since we seem to have some